Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching the plane bagel. Major news
circulating in the finance space online
this past Friday as we got the breaking
headline from finance Twitter or Finance
X, whatever we're calling it these days,
that Federal Reserve Chair Jerome Powell
had abandoned reason for madness and
would be throwing away America's 2%
inflation target rate. But during a
keynote speech at the annual Jackson
Hole Symposium, the Fed chair caving to
pressure and turning dovish, shifting
from an inflation targeting regime to a
focus on employment, telling the boys to
put on the space helmets cuz we're
firing up the money printers again. A
shocking update that many were quick to
share and lament online, warning that
this would pave the way for higher
inflation, possibly even stagflation,
and the spiraling collapse of the US
dollar. All of which incredibly
concerning
if any of it were real. Uh, but turns
out this was just some wild
misinformation we saw really take flight
over this weekend, stemming from a
pretty severe misinterpretation of what
was actually said at this keynote
speech. You see, on Friday at this
annual event hosted by the Kansas City
Federal Reserve Bank, we had this highly
anticipated speech from the Federal
Reserve Chair Drone Powell where he was
expected to update people on his views
on the central bank's policy moving
forward. And not long after the event,
we had this unsourced screenshot start
circulating online, seemingly suggesting
that the Fed had made this drastic move
to abandon its 2% inflation target. And
for a lot of big profiles is proof
enough to start raising the alarm and
spreading the word that the uh Federal
Reserve had started the path to
hyperinflation. So to get to the bottom
of this, I decided to do the
unthinkable, to venture where no one
else dared to.
I I read the 20-minute speech
transcript. And what's crazy is that
while this bullet point technically
isn't incorrect, it's just being wildly
misinterpreted. And far from abandoning
the 2% target, it's actually reaffirmed
in many points throughout the speech.
There were indicators that the bank
might be shifting its policy towards
something that eases its current
restrictive policies, which is why we
did see markets and the crypto market
jump on Friday. Uh but far from whatever
we saw kind of being claimed online. And
if you want to see the speeches for
yourself, I'll include links in the
description down below to the transcript
as well as the live stream of the
speech. Uh, but to quickly summarize it
here, essentially we have Jerome Powell
highlighting that while the US is
currently experiencing relatively tame
inflation and unemployment rates, things
are a little jittery, if not curious, to
quote the actual word he used. With the
US seeing both supply and demand for
employment falling and GDP growth
slowing, indicating that while yes,
unemployment was still near historical
lows, there were risks around that.
something highlighted by the massive
downward revision to the labor data we
saw in the July report with tariffs,
decreased immigration, and changes in
government tax policies, spending and
regulations being key factors impacting
economic growth and productivity in the
US. He also highlighted that inflation
face upside risk because of tariffs, uh,
which even though they should just lead
to this sort of one-time impact, could
translate into a longerterm, more
persistent high inflation rate, which
was something the bank would need to
monitor for. However, with the bank's
policy being in restrictive territory
and employment facing these downward
pressures, quote, "The baseline outlook
and the shifting balance of risks may
warrant adjusting our policy stance."
And that line was probably the biggest
takeaway from the speech. As you are
probably aware, the Federal Reserve has
this dual mandate of both ensuring price
stability and trying to achieve maximum
employment. And in the speech, it was
more or less being highlighted that
while the Federal Reserve saw risks
around inflation and intended to keep
trying to keep things around 2% that it
was also seeing this weakness in
employment and didn't want to basically
neglect this data and that it would
consider how information developed
moving forward in deciding whether to
make a change. But then Richard, you
might ask, where did this idea that the
Federal Reserve would be abandoning its
target come from? Well, again, that
seems to stem from this widely shared
screenshot of a uh unsourced bullet
point that turns out to come from this
Bloomberg article with Bloomberg being a
fairly reputable business journal. And
if you read the quote, it does sound
like the Federal Reserve is moving away
from targeting inflation in favor of
focusing on employment. But if you look
ever so closely, you'll see the word
average in there, which is playing a
monumental role in changing the meaning
of this uh bullet point here. You see,
as part of the speech, Powell provided
an update to the Federal Reserve's
statement on longerrun goals and
monetary policy strategy, which is
essentially just a public statement
highlighting the Fed's framework for
managing its dual mandate of again uh
promoting maximum employment and
maintaining stable prices. And Pal
announced that with this update to the
statement, the bank would be moving away
from its makeup strategy around
inflation. You see, after the 2008
financial crisis, the US had this weird
situation where it was dealing with both
very low interest rates and low
inflation. While that might sound like a
kind of best case scenario, it did
present a unique challenge to the
central bank because if the US economy
suddenly would need monetary stimulus,
there wasn't anywhere further that rates
could go. They were already near their
effective lower bound, which limited
their options for kind of intervening.
So in 2020, the bank changed its
approach with inflation targeting to
focus instead on a long-term average
inflation rate. Uh meaning that if there
was say a two or threeear period where
inflation was below 2%, they would allow
inflation to reach above 2% uh in the
following years so that over the long
term it would reach that 2% average
inflation rate. However, with the
pandemic and the surging in inflation we
saw during that period, it became
evident how easily inflation can get out
of hand if it's allowed to creep above
this target. even with what were assumed
to be transitory pressures. So, the big
update that we saw with this 2025 speech
is that the Federal Reserve will be
abandoning its long-term average
inflation target of 2%, this so-called
makeup strategy, and just reverting to
its uh strategy from before the 2020
update of just targeting 2% every year.
That's it. That's the big update that
led to all this misinformation. And the
bullet point is technically correct
because the Fed is abandoning its
average inflation makeup strategy and is
putting more focus on employment. But
the crux of the speech was that in this
environment where you have sort of these
factors pulling in different directions
that they would try to take a balanced
approach. So while I agree that the
bullet point in isolation is very easy
to misunderstand and maybe even be
borderline misleading by itself, you can
see that what was circulating was just
flatout wrong. Now, I will highlight
that the speech was seen as a meaningful
shift in the bank's rhetoric up until
this point. Uh we had recently heard
that members of the FOMC were in favor
of holding rates steady, lowering the
chance of a September rate cut and
Jerome Powell had highlighted that until
the tariff situation stabilized, there
wasn't much motivation to start lowering
rates. But with the speech, the Fed has
now opened the door to a possible pivot,
highlighting, hey, uh we don't want to
kill the economy with rates that are too
high given the risks that we face. Uh so
there is room for pivot moving forward
and there is a lot of pressure on the
Federal Reserve to do just that. Uh
outside of the literal pressure coming
from uh Donald Trump himself. We have
also seen liquidity in the financial
system decrease. You may have also seen
the alarm bell tweet circulating around
the so-called reverse repo facility
being drained. That was going to be the
topic of this video before uh the
weekend. But just to quickly touch on
that doesn't mean that there's no longer
repo money available, but it is a sign
of financial institutions being less
willing to lend out their money. And
with the central bank also carrying out
quantitative tightening, that's also
pressure on liquidity. As the bonds that
the central bank bought mature and don't
get kind of rolled over, that leads to
money being pulled out of the system,
which again can be quite restrictive.
But importantly, the Federal Reserve
hasn't committed to easing monetary
policy yet. Yes, there was again this uh
change in tone of the speech, but it
effectively amounted to, hey, we're
going to see what data comes out and be
open to the idea of shifting based on
how things update in the future. But
there wasn't any commitment to a rate
cut in the near term. And even if there
was a rate cut, rates could still remain
above that neutral level, meaning they'd
still be restrictive since that neutral
rate is the point at which interest
rates are neither uh stimulating nor
depressing the economy. We've covered on
this channel before how rate cuts don't
inherently lead to higher market returns
since they're usually in response to
other economic factors that are
simultaneously depressing economic
activity. So, while not all the
discussion around the Friday speech was
uh misinformation, there were people
being critical of this rhetoric shift,
highlighting that's too early for the
Federal Reserve to consider switching to
rate cuts and risking the stagflation.
But even there, it's worth acknowledging
that nothing was committed to with the
speech. We don't for sure have a rate
cut coming in September, even with this
change of tone. And with Federal Reserve
members having previously highlighted
the need to tolerate periods of
liquidity friction to normalize Fed
involvement in the markets, it's far
less certain exactly how far the bank
would go with stimulus measures, whether
that would involve QE or other
interventions if it does take that
route. Anyway, that's more or less the
story and all I wanted to say about it.
Of course, people make mistakes. It's
easy to see how this bullet point was
misinterpreted, but it's also not the
first time we've had this sort of
misinformation wave in the finance space
about some apocalyptic dollar headline
that turned out to be fake. Uh you might
remember the end of the petro dollar
agreement, this fable document that was
set to expire and uh pose the end of the
US dollar. Turned out that the actual
agreement that people seem to be
referencing had nothing to do with a
petro dollar arrangement. It's
frustrating because all this could be
avoided if people just took the 10
minutes to read the the source material,
the primary document that they're
spewing all these opinions on. So, if
nothing else, hopefully it serves as a
reminder that on social media, you you
got to be careful. Uh because these
types of posts, especially in the
finance space, can influence people's
investment decisions. And whether it's
my own content or someone else you
follow on YouTube, Twitter, whatever it
is, just remember that substantial
claims require substantial evidence,
right? not some obscure screenshot of
someone else's summary of what allegedly
happened.